Here's this woman who knew everything about me, and I knew nothing about her. I don't even remember saying goodbye. PSW: All I could think about that day was that it was late September in New York, and I was wearing white jeans. (Laughter) You don't wear white after Labor Day in New York. There was a knock at the door, and all I could think about was, here I stand in my wrong jeans. And then I saw these big, blue eyes I love so much, and they were staring back at me in disbelief. And I thought, "Oh, this is not going to be easy." When one person in a family transitions, the entire family transitions whether they want to or not. Now, for those on the fringes it was easy. The liberals said, "Oh, wonderful! She's found her truth, how delightful." And the conservatives said, "That's messed up, I'm out of here." (Laughter) But for my family, neither extreme was going to work. Their anger, their hurt, their love and loyalty -- all of it had to be brought on to the road of trials. JW: Was it all a lie? Every game of catch in the front yard, the Mets season tickets -- was that with my dad or was that with her? I remember this one time, my dad took me on a bike ride through Heckscher Park to teach me about sex. He explained the parts of the body that I now know he wished weren't hers. Had my father ever even existed? Now, grief -- grief is without rules. Grief borrows your car without asking, wrecks it and then doesn't apologize. And I was a wreck. This was heavy. I retreated into myself. I was angry. I felt betrayed. And I guess I should have known by the fact that you encouraged me to be a Mets fan that you were preparing me for life's really big disappointments. (Laughter) That's true. And yet, there were the games of catch, and there were the season tickets and bacon, egg and cheese sandwiches every Saturday from the best bagel place on Long Island. My father lived this life he didn't want to live, but he lived it so that I could have a dad. I stopped wondering if my dad had ever existed. He had existed -- willfully, consciously, intentionally -- each and every day of my growing up. For that, I was thankful. Paula's body was hers now and her transformation was complete, but my transformation was just beginning. I had another trial, another journey, another choice to heed my father's advice and continue down that narrow path. PSW: So most days I believe there is a God. Tuesdays and Thursdays can be tough, and any day that you're on the New Jersey Turnpike. I mean, really, you know? (Laughter) It's hard to believe in God when your soul is in the wrong body. Still, somehow I ended up in ministry. When I lost all my jobs, it was nothing personal. It's what religious tribes do. They believe an enemy is necessary for the tribe to survive, so where no enemy exists, they create one. Right now, sexual minorities are the enemy; my departure was swift and sure. I was surprised when my son left his job teaching in West Philadelphia to go into the ministry. I did not see that one coming. And now I wondered: What would he do? I didn't have to wait that long to find an answer. Six months after that first visit, he invited me back to New York. JW: The designers of the Brooklyn Bridge, they had their share of bad luck. John Roebling, he died shortly after the bridge's construction began. His son Washington took over, but he suffered from decompression sickness. His wife Emily became the surrogate executive engineer who oversaw the bridge's completion. Father and son, John and Washington, done in by their work. It was this sunny day in May and my father and I sat in the shadow of that Brooklyn Bridge. Would our lives follow the Roeblings' -- father and son, done in by our work? My father thought that her friends in church would carry her through her transition, and they did not. They ditched her and they clung to me. I was the pastor of a new church in Brooklyn. This wonderful group of forward-thinking people, and yet, we were financially tied to really conservative churches. To hold space for Paula meant jeopardizing our own church's livelihood. I sort of straddled the line between these warring worlds. So I said to my dad, "Dad, I still live and work in your old world. Is it possible that you might extend an olive branch for my sake?" And her response was impassioned. You said to me, "Do you have any idea what it feels like to finally show yourself to your true friends and have them completely reject you? To ask you to live a lie? Do you know what that feels like?" And I didn't know what that felt like. But I knew I had a decision to make. It was the decision to continue down that narrow path through nights, but for the first time, I caught a glimpse of light. I cannot ask my father to be anything other than her true self. (Applause) PSW: So as we sat by the river that day, Jonathan talked about his pain, his suffering, his grief, his confusion. He brought all of himself to that conversation, and it tore at me to be the cause of such pain. But as he talked, there was something redemptive going on, full of tension but possibility, grounded in that narrow path. He said, "This is always going to be hard. It always will be. But Dad, I love you." My son is the best of me and more. He's bold and strong, sensitive and thoughtful. I guess you could say, he's an alpha male who's gentle. JW: It was time for my daughters to meet their -- Paula. We went back to my apartment, and my daughters were coloring at the dining room table, and there was this awkward silence. And finally, my youngest asked a single, confident question. "So, Grandpa, do you have a penis?" (Laughter) And after the tension abated and the laughter subsided, my girls took their grandpa back into their room and showed her their new toys, and they christened her with a new name. They called her "GrandPaula." (Laughter) PSW: So this past summer, I had all five of my granddaughters at my home, there in the foothills of the Rocky Mountains. We went swimming in the cool waters of the river that flows through our little town. And one day, one of Jonathan's girls said to me, "GrandPaula, can we go tubing on the river?" And I said, "Well, you know, I'd really wait until your daddy gets here for that. That feels to me like that ought to be his call." And she said, "Oh, but GrandPaula, he'll exactly make the same decision you would. He's a lot like you, you know." (Laughter) And I thought, yeah, he is a lot like me, both of us determined to find the narrow path and follow it through the long, dark night, all the way to the light of dawn. JW: Have you ever noticed that a child who is secure, a child who knows love, that child will dance? They wave their arms, they kick their legs to music that only they can hear. It's the music of a child who is safe and unharmed and wholly loved. The day after my children met their GrandPaula, she took them to go get doughnuts, and I watched as they walked down the street, and my girls took my father's arms, and they danced. My father's arms swung wildly. You bought them one too many doughnuts, because you always do -- (Laughter) I watched my older daughter take a bite of her doughnut, and she unleashed two jumps and a twirl. It was perfect. That narrow path, it always has its share of burdens and challenges. But I was certain that we were going to see this through to redemption. I looked at my dad and I looked at my girls who were dancing and eating their doughnuts, and I said aloud to no one in particular, I said, "This ... this is how God sees my dad." My father was literally born again. And by choosing the narrow path of redemption, I was born again with her. Thank you. (Applause and cheers)
Ahí estaba esa mujer que sabía todo sobre mí y yo no sabía nada de ella. Ni siquiera recuerdo haber dicho adiós. PSW: Ese día solo era capaz de pensar que era finales de septiembre en Nueva York y yo llevaba pantalones blancos. (Risas) No se lleva blanco después del Día del Trabajo en Nueva York. Llamaron a la puerta y en lo único que pensaba era que aquí estoy con los pantalones equivocados. Y entonces vi esos enormes ojos azules que tanto adoro que me miraban con incredulidad. Y pensé: "Oh, esto no va a ser fácil". Cuando alguien de la familia hace la transición, también lo hace toda la familia, ya sea que lo quieran o no. Para los que lo ven desde fuera es fácil. Los liberales decían: "¡Oh, estupendo! Ella ha encontrado su verdad, es maravilloso". Y los conservadores decían: "Eso está fatal, me largo". (Risas) Pero para mi familia, ningún extremo iba a funcionar. Su enfado, su dolor, su amor y su lealtad... todo tenía que pasar por el camino de las pruebas. JW: ¿Había sido todo mentira? Cada vez que jugábamos en el jardín, las entradas de los Mets... ¿habían pasado con mi padre o con ella? Recuerdo una vez que mi padre me llevó a montar en bici por el parque Hecksche para hablarme sobre sexo. Me explicó las partes del cuerpo que ahora sé que él deseaba que no fueran suyas. ¿Había llegado a existir mi padre? El dolor... el dolor no tiene normas. El dolor toma prestado tu auto sin permiso, lo destroza y luego no se disculpa. Y yo estaba destrozado. Esto era duro. Me refugié en mí mismo. Estaba enfadado. Me sentía traicionado. Debería haber sabido por el hecho de que me animabas a seguir a los Mets que me preparabas para las grandes decepciones de la vida. (Risas) Es verdad. Y aún así estaban los juegos en el jardín, las entradas de temporada y los sándwhiches de tocino, huevo y queso de los sábados del mejor sitio de bagels de Long Island. Mi padre vivió una vida que no quería vivir, pero lo hizo para que yo pudiera tener un padre. Dejé de preguntarme si mi padre había existido. Había existido, de manera obstinada, consciente e intencional, todos los días de mi infancia. Le estaba agradecido por eso. El cuerpo de Paula ahora era suyo y su transformación estaba completa, pero la mía estaba empezando. Tenía otra prueba, otro viaje, otra elección para seguir el consejo de continuar por el camino estrecho. PSW: La mayoría de los días creo que hay un Dios. Los martes y los jueves pueden ser duros y cualquier día que pasen por el New Jersey Turnpike. Ya saben, ¿no? (Risas) Es difícil creer en Dios cuando tu alma está en el cuerpo equivocado. Aún así, de alguna manera acabé en el clero. Cuando perdí todos mis trabajos no fue nada personal. Es lo que hacen las tribus religiosas. Creen que hace falta un enemigo para que sobreviva la tribu, así que si no hay enemigo, lo crean. Ahora mismo el enemigo son las minorías sexuales; mi salida fue rápida y segura. Me sorprendí cuando mi hijo dejó su trabajo de profesor en Filadelfia oeste para meterse en el clero. No me lo esperaba. Y entonces me pregunté: ¿qué haría él? No tuve que esperar tanto tiempo para encontrar una respuesta. Seis meses después de esa primera visita me invitó otra vez a Nueva York. JW: Los diseñadores del puente de Brooklyn tuvieron su dosis de mala suerte. John Roebling murió poco después de que comenzara la construcción del puente. Su hijo Washington tomó el relevo pero tuvo síndrome de descompresión. Su mujer, Emily, pasó a ser la ingeniera ejecutiva sustituta y supervisó la finalización del puente. Padre e hijo, John y Washington, vencidos por su trabajo. Un día soleado de mayo mi padre y yo estábamos sentados a la sombra de dicho puente. ¿Serían nuestras vidas como las de los Roebling... padre e hijo vencidos por nuestro trabajo? Mi padre pensaba que sus amigos de la iglesia le acompañarían durante su transición, pero no lo hicieron. La abandonaron y se aferraron a mí. Yo era pastor en una nueva iglesia de Brooklyn. Era un grupo maravilloso de gente progresista y aún así estábamos económicamente atados a iglesias muy conservadoras. Hacer sitio a Paula significaba poner en peligro el sustento de nuestra iglesia. Yo estaba en la línea entre estos dos mundos enfrentados. Así que le dije a mi padre, "Papá, yo todavía vivo y trabajo en tu antiguo mundo. ¿Cabe la posibilidad de que hagas una ofrenda de paz por mí?". Y su respuesta fue apasionada. Me dijiste: "¿Tienes idea de lo que se siente cuando por fin uno se muestra a sus verdaderos amigos y ellos te rechazan de lleno? ¿Que te pidan vivir una mentira? ¿Sabes qué se siente?". Y yo no sabía qué se sentía. Pero sabía que tenía que tomar una decisión. Era la decisión de continuar por ese camino estrecho por las noches, pero por pimera vez vi un destello de luz. No puedo pedir a mi padre que sea otra cosa que no fuera su verdadero yo. (Aplausos) PSW: Ese día, sentados a la orilla del río, Jonathan habló de su dolor, su sufrimiento, su confusión. En esa conversación puso todo sobre la mesa y me destrozó ser la causa de ese dolor. Pero mientras hablaba había algo de redención, llena de tensión pero de posibilidad, anclado en el camino estrecho. Él dijo: "Esto siempre va a ser duro. Siempre lo será. Pero papá, te quiero". Mi hijo es lo mejor de mí y más. Es valiente y fuerte, sensible y considerado. Supongo que se podría decir que es un macho alfa delicado. JW: Era hora de que mis hijas conocieran a su... Paula. Volvimos a mi apartamento, mis hijas estaban coloreando sobre la mesa del comedor y se produjo un silencio incómodo. Y de repente, la más pequeña hizo una sola pregunta con mucha seguridad. "Abuelo, ¿tienes pene?". (Risas) Y cuando se redujeron la tensión y las risas, mis hijas se llevaron a su abuelo a su habitación, le enseñaron sus juguetes nuevos y le bautizaron con un nombre nuevo. La llamaron "PaulAbuela". (Risas) PSW: El verano pasado tuve a mis cinco nietas en casa, en las laderas de las Montañas Rocosas. Fuimos a nadar en las aguas más frías del río que corre por nuestro pueblecito. Y un día, una de las hijas de Jonathan me dijo: "PaulAbuela, ¿podemos hacer tubing en el río?". Y les dije: "Bueno... yo esperaría hasta que su padre llegara. Creo que él es quien debería decidirlo". Y ella dijo: "Pero PaulAbuela, él tomaría exactamente la misma decisión que tú. Se parece mucho a ti, sabes". (Risas) Y yo pensé, sí, se parece mucho a mí, los dos estamos empeñados en encontrar el camino estrecho y en seguirlo a través de la larga y oscura noche hasta el amanecer. JW: ¿Alguna vez han notado que un niño que tiene seguridad, que conoce el amor, es un niño que bailará? Mueven sus brazos, mueven las piernas al ritmo de una música que solo oyen ellos. Es la música de un niño que está seguro e ileso y es tremendamente querido. El día después de que mis hijas conocieran a PaulAbuela, ella les llevó a comprar donuts, yo las miraba mientras ellas caminaban y mis hijas tomaron los brazos de mi padre y bailaron. Los brazos de mi padre se movían a lo loco. Les compraste demasiados donuts porque siempre lo haces... (Risas) Vi a mi hija mayor tomar un bocado del donut y nos deleitó con dos saltos y un giro. Fue perfecto. Ese camino estrecho tiene siempre sus cargas y sus retos. Pero estaba seguro de que persistiríamos hasta la redención. Miré a mi padre y miré a mis hijas que estaban bailando y comiendo sus donuts y dije en alto a nadie en concreto, dije: "Así... así es como Dios ve a mi padre". Mi padre volvió a nacer, literalmente. Y al elegir el camino estrecho de la redención yo volví a nacer con ella. Gracias. (Aplausos y ovación)